well hey everybody good to see again
dr. Andy Galvin 55-minute Fitz this is
another video in my giant series on all
things fatigue conditioning endurance
one of the hell you want to call it I
don't care now to give you a little help
here
we've answered a bunch of questions in
this context already you can see other
videos both fifty five and five and
maybe even a 25-minute version I don't
remember exactly when we answered things
like endurance how I split it up how I
program for it so how are right
different workouts for different types
of endurance that video is important for
you to watch all those videos before you
watch this one because we're going to
get to eventually is how and why I
program is based on the physiology of
about to explain to you well and more
specifically what we're gonna get to in
the next video in this series and what
you can do about it and attritional in
training lines once you understand why
things break down with different types
of endurance then you can fix them
accordingly all right so what I'm really
suggesting is if you haven't seen those
videos where I answer questions 1 & 2
what does endurance how do I program for
it go back right now I promise you come
back to this video after you watch that
if also you're trying to skip ahead and
go to the next version the next video in
this series which is a 55 minute
physiology of endurance video where I
answer questions like why we get tired
in the first place what our vo2 max is
this is a term we hear all the time with
endurance but you maybe not know exactly
what it is why we breathe and why is
this breath work becoming so popular
right now is it true not well I wouldn't
watch that video either without watching
this one so my order of operations
number one the programming what is
endurance videos number two this one and
number three 55 minute physiology of
endurance so in this particular video
what I want to do is drill down deep on
how we actually make energy for human
movement if you're thinking to yourself
are going to watch this I had X fist
class I had I know oxidation glycolytic
blah blah blah that's not the whole
picture here you're going to really do
yourself a disservice by skipping this
video and going to the third ones we
will cover that a little bit but I
promise you will do it in a fashion
that's a little more entertaining
it's a little more correct and we're
gonna fill in some gaps so if you've had
an ex fizz before like you're one of my
students watching right now you've had
expose I know you have maybe a couple of
times we're gonna take some of those
concepts build on them and it'll be a
really nice refresher but we'll do a
better job of putting in context of
human performance of wine actually
matters if you've never had xvid on't
fret I think you can get through this
video just fine ninety five percent or
so retention right here without our rang
EXIF is the way we learned it alright so
I think there's something in here for a
little bit for everyone will be excited
and we'll jump right into it looking
forward to it thanks for sticking around
and let's get going
alright before we get started let's make
sure really quickly we're on the same
page in terms of definitions so I'll use
endurance fatigue conditioning fairly
synonymously in these series of videos
now they're not the exact same thing but
they're close enough for now and I just
mean your ability to endure something
difficult and keep going in previous
videos you're gonna have to go back and
watch I think I had a 25 minute version
and maybe even a 5 minute version this
but I split up endurance into a bunch of
different levels now I'm not going to
cover them here I'm just gonna give you
the condensed version
I'll call muscular endurance like your
ability of the local muscle itself to
manage fatigue think how many pushups
can you do in a minute right think reps
to fail think the burn in an actual
local muscle kind of going from there
I'll just combine everything together
and call it high-intensity think
intervals think Sprint's on the track a
pill we are getting you know really
tired an aerobic conditioning throwing
up except for something in the thirty
Seconds to two three four five minutes
of really hard-ass work I'll call that
all high-intensity and then pass that
further I'll just call it long duration
endurance so this is me your more
classic cardio your sustained effort I
prefer the term long duration endurance
this is the sec you t'v or continuous
work maybe some small undulations and
intensity but for really long time
domains now this is going to be
important because as I'm going through
this discussion and particularly at the
end while I after I've explained to you
what happens physiologically the causes
are fatigue I'm gonna differentiate
between these different things so we
understand well what causes a fatigue
for
muscular endurance what can I do about
it what causes fatigue for high
intensity stuff what can I do about it
and then the same for long duration I'll
cover a little bit nutritionally that's
maybe in some other videos if you're
nice and you ask pretty please below ask
me maybe I'll do that but really more
about programming and really the focus
of this big large video it's gonna be a
long one anyways I don't need to add
more to it so really I just want to
focus on the physiology what's happening
maybe we'll come back later and make
some more videos giving you the
practical tips right you'll get some but
but not after minutes no while we're
here by the way I want to give you a
quick shout out to my friends on the
screen here you can see Chris Moore and
that deadlift pull good friend of mine
coach Mick G Michael gold Rick CTP and
Alex Macklin from barbell Shrugged crew
and fame doing their intervals there and
then of course the sensational miss
Boone there and her Spartan Race so
nonetheless let's go ahead and move on
and the first thing we have to do is
talk about why we get tired from this
perspective I'm only going to talk about
physiology we're not going to get into
the brain or psychology or motivation in
like that just physiologically and
mostly bio energetically why we get
tired well it's really a con effect of
two different things or it's a
combination and we failed to be able to
produce sufficient ATP or energy now
quick reminder ATP is the energy
currency of all biological cells it's a
little molecule we have to make to
produce energy so what happens is we for
some reason and there's a whole host
we're gonna get into our reasons we
don't create sufficient ATP or energy to
meet the demands of the exercise I'm
moving muscle Tex energy I've got to
make that demand this also could be
happening or it could not be happening
we don't necessarily know kind of
depends a situation but you could just
be simply generating too much waste the
good example here is typically with
aerobic or steady-state exercise it's
not really a huge issue of creating too
much waste it's a problem of being able
to create enough energy now an aerobic
or burn stuff fatigue stuff like real
high again make you throw up that's
typically not an issue of not being able
to create enough energy it's mostly not
be able to handle the waste so let's get
into these
a lot more detail and we're going to
spend the bulk of our time dealing or at
least initially here dealing with number
one which is not having enough pure ATP
now if you've had an exercise physiology
class this is gonna feel like a little
bit of a review there but I'll put it in
context of performance I think I could
do it a little bit better than most of
your teachers so basics a lot of you
have heard now I also have a I know at
least a five minute video on this you
should go back and watch that one so
I'll give the quick version here but
you'll see a guest appearance from my my
favorite dog goes face killer running
around and the analogy I like to give
with wood and and and fire I'll bring up
there but for now here's the quick
overview they're basically for what
we'll call substrates or things you can
use to create energy in a human cell
particularly skeletal muscle starting up
number one we'll talk is carbohydrate
and you can see the image I'm using
there is the picture of the hamburger
bond fat and protein
now when I say carbohydrate I don't just
mean bread or grains okay yeah in fact
go watch one of my contrition videos
where I talk about what carbohydrates
actually are and distinguishing them
between fats and and how those things
actually work I've covered that
extensively in hours of videos now on
other products so for now carbohydrates
fat I know there's protein and cheese
but it's estates fan I know there's fat
in a hamburger but I just was thinking
about hamburgers when I made this so I
kind of broke them all down right well
there's another one that's called
phosphocreatine now it is different than
fast cars are protein the fact that is
not a macronutrient it's not a food you
consume but it is a direct path probably
the mode I'm probably definitely the
most direct path to ATP so I like to put
it up here is kind of a fourth one right
even though it's not technically another
macronutrient so here's what really
happens regardless of what we're using
for the fuel the whole damn point is to
get to ATP which stands for adenosine
triphosphate which is why you can see
those three P's standing on top of those
little flags if you all have that ATP
molecule so triphosphate now effectively
the analogy I like to use is think of
protein not as a source of cellular
energy now as I just showed you you can
use it to make ATP we'll get into this
later but
not the primary reason we need ingest
protein so what I would say is if you're
trying to create something of importance
in the cell so so you're trying to add
more muscle mass or you want to recover
the muscle mass that you damage in a
given workout or build a new immune cell
or a thousand other things that you can
use for protein all right we use protein
for a lot of different things you have a
scrap a bunch of hunk metal scrap metal
kind of laying around somewhere you can
see in the image here you've got a big
piece of metal there and it's not
particularly useful for anything you
want to repurpose all that now so you've
got the supply you've got all of this
scrap metal simmer now in the case of
protein we'll refer to that as amino
acids so amino acids come together to
make up a protein so if you've got a
whole pool of amino acid somewhere but
they're not in the organization they're
not making up the particular protein you
like well then you have to do something
with it in other words it is
tremendously effective supply so one of
the major reasons we ingest or consume
protein is so that we have sufficient
amounts of amino acids available so that
we can combine them in the orders we
want to make the particular proteins we
want covered extensively in other videos
but we make about a hundred thousand
different types of proteins in the body
so you've got your amino acids well in
order to make those into a protein that
takes a lot of energy it's a really
metabolically costly process so in order
to do that where you gonna get that
energy from enter this analogy so go
back and watch the other video but the
quick version all right if in my opinion
you can think of phosphorus in as like a
match imagine you're making a fire and
you're making a a camp fire if you up
well if you take a match which is made
of wood and some stuff in the end the
benefit of using a match to make a fire
as it likes extremely quickly but the
downside is it burns out really fast I
mean if you've got a match and held it
there until it burned all the way bottom
I don't know what it would be ten
seconds twenty seconds is that 35 who
know some less than a minute or so
matter of seconds well a carbohydrate
which is also made of wood by the way in
this particular case this is carbon what
I'm talking about well think of it like
a newspaper a newspaper is a good way to
start a fire but if you're
ire fire is based on newspaper the
downside is I mean if you put a whole
newspaper into a fire how long until it
burns out
I don't know twenty two minutes three
minutes four minutes some something like
that right it's a little bit longer than
creatine court and they'll probably by
an order of magnitude but it's still
pretty dang short it'd be the pain in
the ass to make an entire camp fire
which is newspaper fat on the other hand
functions more like wood and so again
that the nice part here is what you'll
notice is wood newspaper newspaper is
made from wood right and the match made
from wood are all based on the same
structural components which are carbon
we'll come back to this later but that's
really really really important there big
long carbon chains fossil creatine is a
short one right the carbohydrates are a
little bit longer six or so well fats
are basically infinitely long so the
benefit of using wood for a fire in this
case this is not as easy to light it
takes some time to get going it's kind
of a pain in the answer is literally a
time dying right you you won't have a
fire going I promise you you take a
match your fire is going immediately all
right
you somehow light up a piece of
newspaper that fire gonna happen
immediately you can't light many forms
of wood on fire immediately it takes a
couple of minutes of smoldering and
getting them going right but the benefit
is they last exponentially longer almost
I'm basically infinitely longer than the
carbohydrates of the protein and so
that's really the benefit of our going
for we have to understand then it's not
that one of these fuels is better than
another in fact we'll talk about the
pros and cons of all of them and how
they relate to beauty it's just the fact
that they have pros and cons right and
so a healthy high functioning athlete in
most particular cases our general human
should have an appropriate ability to
use which fuel source is best given the
demands of the situation and that
changes based on shift when you change
the demand or the situation what you're
asking the body to do so we need to
recognize that and then we can take our
training and our nutrition and apply
that propria based on what we're trying
to get out of wrapping what's our
purpose what's our goal what are we
training for nonetheless if you do this
properly and you use the phosphocreatine
carbohydrate
fazt to generate the most optimal amount
of ATP you could use that energy to go
back and do things a whole number of
things but one of them would be
combining amino acids into a sequence to
make a protein that you particularly
want and this is our relationship with
what we call protein synthesis and
energy metabolism right it's one of the
major things we do with this so in the
analogy I gave a second ago if we've got
this whole hunk of metal on all this
scrap around and this is kind of a
junkie piece of thing and we use and we
invest some energy and we make a nice
big smouldering fire at fire it's a
proper temperature that's not wasteful
but when we need to melt it we can
recombine that metal and make it into
something more useful like a giant
awesome sword all right if you didn't
laugh at that you're breaking my heart I
know it's a super lame joke that
probably didn't translate very well onto
YouTube but it sometimes makes like
three of my students laugh in class and
I like it because it's an awesome sword
so to hell with you one of the major
points I'm really getting at here is if
we take this concept of aerobic and
anaerobic metabolism you need to talk
about how these things interact spoiler
alert I don't know why we think they're
against each other it's like one's
better than the other and it's fighting
do you want to be this is not how the
system works so a little bit of backup
of what actually happens with robic and
anaerobic aerobic means oxygen or
needing oxygen anaerobic this means you
don't have to have oxygen available to
produce energy so when we talk about
those macronutrients and and
phosphocreatine where on the spectrum do
these live in other words when I use
phosphocreatine to make energy is that
an aerobic process there's an anaerobic
process what about fat what about cards
what about protein well if you've had a
little bit of of ex phase are you one of
mine one of my students in class right
now I know you know most of these things
but you probably don't know all of it
and maybe you're maybe you're a little
bit jumped up it's been a couple of
years since XP so you're kind of like I
don't know exactly so let's lay this out
really quickly so on the same page now
first of all that little image I just
flashed up on the screen it's called a
mitochondria any time you hear the word
aerobic you can automatically assume
it's happening
and this plays a critical role to
fatigue I'm not too teaching next fizz
to teach you Exodus and promise you this
explains why some things cause exercise
wise cause more or less fatigue and what
the hell to do about a train why isn't
attrition lines so when you hear
oxidation we hear Rubik you know this is
happening the mitochondria if it's not
happening in Maya Kandra it means it's
happening outside of it in the cell
cytoplasm all right so you're picking up
a muscle cell it's got all these
mitochondria inside of it and then
there's this other place that's outside
of the mitochondria it's still inside
the cell anaerobic metabolism happens in
that other space aerobic happens in this
mitochondria all right so now if we
start from the easy in the spectrum I
know you know this and you realize this
if I flashed up phosphocreatine where
would this go on this spectrum of
anaerobic - aerobic it's phosphocreatine
metabolism anaerobic process on the
wrist you have to have oxygen to do it
what do you know well the answer is no
right is that it is entirely 100%
anaerobic process in fact the
stoichiometry is favorable for
phosphocreatine in that in fact that it
takes one phosphocreatine to make one
ATP it's a very direct one-step process
not a lot going on here tremendous
benefit downside we'll get to know in a
minute
what about fat whereas fat on the
spectrum well fat is actually a hundred
percent aerobic ooh interesting so now
what we can see happen in the muscle
cell is when I want to make energy
extremely quickly just between these two
which one when I choose
well obviously phosphocreatine right
number one because it's not in the
mitochondria it's actually outside of
that and so I don't have to go through
these extra steps which I'm going to
talk about in a second but I can just
have a one step process boom make ATP
fat on the other hand has to be broken
down wherever I'm taking it from either
outside of the muscle cell or outside of
the muscle entirely brought up taking
into mitochondria and then using I have
to use aerobic half-way steps to get to
energy from that what this means is
that's going to be a delay there and
there's also a problem is what if I need
that energy and I don't have oxygen like
I'm doing high intensity intervals well
then I'm gonna go back to Crete C but
the downside of creatine is this that
Matt you don't have
much of it you can only store so much of
it in the actual muscle cell now I don't
stole much fat in my mitochondria I
stole my fat in other places throughout
the body so the storage ability of fat
is exponentially higher than
phosphocreatine so again folks it's not
a good or a bad thing there's pros and
cons right the benefit of having music
mitochondria and not storing a
tremendous amount of muscle is I can
store it I'll in limited amounts
throughout the rest of the body and my
adipose tissue well I don't store
phosphocreatine in other places I mean
for the most part so I can only store
the amount that I can hold inside that
muscle cell that's not inside the
mitochondria but the benefit is it's
really quickest right there you probably
know most out already hopefully what
about protein it turns out protein is an
entirely aerobic process as well and so
we're gonna have to run that through
there this is another one of the many
reasons that why it's not a tremendously
good source for ATP in terms of energy
it's also the stoichiometry meaning how
much energy it kind of takes the
chemistry of it the equation how much
energy it takes to break down our
protein it to get ATP versus how much
ATP we actually get or that it's not
tremendously favorable so it's not a
good way it's not a good method to go
about making ATP it's really inefficient
if you will carbohydrates are the peak
final pieces puzzle and the fact that
wait a minute is it aerobic or anaerobic
no no no passive listening here what you
think is it aerobic or anaerobic
well it's kind of a trick is it's a
little bit of both so there's an
anaerobic component to it and anaerobic
component to it so if you see this
spectrum now well we can clearly
identify is ourselves have figured out
escape mechanism in other words I'm
gonna have something that's entirely
anaerobic I might have something that is
entirely aerobic and I have something
that is in between and this gives you
tremendous flexibility and a ton of
resilience right and this is our this is
the whole damn point right one of the
things that separates humans from any
other species especially is our ability
to adapt and survive in any situation
well this is why your system works the
way it does I
have the ability to have something
strong over here it's really effective
in this method it's really effective
over here but sucks another one and then
I'll put something in between and so I
always make sure I can handle at least
minimal amounts of energy production so
with the carbohydrates it starts off and
aerobic Li without oxygen but in order
to completely metabolize carbohydrate I
need to be able to go into oxygen and
this is one of many reasons we often say
things like even an anaerobic athlete
needs to at least have some aerobic
component because that's what's gonna
allow me to recover or that's going to
allow me to be able to do more an
aerobic endurance especially think of
things like repeated sprint ability or a
sport like MMA that I work with that is
kind of anaerobic but you have to do it
so many times in a row and I eventually
ends up being like high intensity
intervals but a bunch of them tons of
them in a row so this really has a huge
aerobic component to it as well and this
is one of the major reasons alright
because during that 10-second wrestling
exchange your striking exchange yeah
you're probably using mostly
carbohydrate for energy but you need to
be able to go aerobic after that to
finish that metabolic breakdown of
carbohydrate because you can be able do
it again if you don't do that
if you have metabolize carbohydrate
anaerobically and don't fully metabolize
it three robic systems you get left with
a tremendous amount of waste we'll get
into what that waste product actually is
do you know what it is I'll give you a
hint
I got another couple of videos already
up maybe buddy if you already watch them
you probably think I know the answer
that's what he covered in that it's one
of the first videos I did so that's our
spectrum that's what we want to keep in
my ass our foundation for how we
generate energy globally for exercise
and performance so little quiz for you
test if I say you're in my class and I
said okay right now today I'm gonna lay
these three food items on a table and
when we come back we meet either two
days from now or a week from now
depending on this class schedule you're
gonna have to take a bite of one of
these three items and I'm gonna leave it
right there in the table in class
there's some rice
open avocado and a big chunk of meat
which one would you take a bite out well
anyone who's reasonable would say I'm
gonna definitely take a bite of that
rice it's not gonna taste great it's
gonna be dehydrated you leave it out for
we could lose some moisture and get real
stale but it won't rot
it won't go rancid by the way those
terms rancid and rot those are kind of
that's the same thing as saying aerobic
leave metabolized or metabolized for
that matter so when I use my fat on my
side for fuel for exercise that's going
rancid I'm kind of not exactly every but
you get the point
right I'm making my love-handle go
rancid I'm metabolizing it and using it
for energy we just don't like it when
it's in our food but we love it when
it's in our fat right that we're trying
to get rid of so point being why is it
when you open an avocado or meat it goes
rinsing well because the fat and the
protein that's in the meat remember it's
aerobic so if you expose meats sorry fat
or protein rather to oxygen it starts
metabolizing it starts going down in
fact any of you've ever had a good say I
was just um at a steak house last couple
nights ago and I had a 120-day aged 8
ounce ribeye and it was like 89 or 90
bucks or something like that well what
that means if you don't know is they
take that ribeye and leave it out
hanging for 120 days yeah they let it
rot basically and then they come
actually get this green film kind of
brown film in the answer they come out
shave that film off and they have this
amazing piece of meat and why is it
amazing why is it super expensive why
are its aged meat more well because when
you at a below sit like that you let it
go rancid it gets a lot more tender it
loses its toughness because you've half
metabolized it right you've made it into
mush really really tender if you a steak
from something just killed an hour ago
it won't be as tender as something that
you aged for 30 days or 49 days or
hundred 20 days or whatever and that's
because you're letting it go rinse and
you're letting it be metabolized
right then that whole like cutting off
with the green stuff that's that's
totally true
so if you've got a good piece of tender
steak or me it's it's been let have some
funk girl for a while and they just
shaved it off made it nice and Brie
avocado too everyone liked it of course
this is blown up in the last decade
right
everyone knows avocados are primarily
fat so when I open that damn thing up
and I expose it starts metabolizing so
any of you cooks out there and you well
least pseudo cooks up you know when the
loves guacamole like I do knows when you
open up the flush I'm an avocado the
first thing you do if you're not kind of
just immediately or eat it immediately
is you cover with a little bit of citric
acid right lime juice lemon juice
something like that maybe just some salt
and the reason you do that is because
the acid the citric acid right from the
citric fruit well acids stop metabolism
we'll go over this later but if you put
yourself in an extremely high acidic
environment enzymes don't work a little
bit enzyme a little bit acid really
helps them a lot of it they don't work
and so you can stop them attacking the
metabolic process of the fat or the meat
for that matter what are we been doing
for hundreds of years to prison before
have refrigerators you take a piece of
meat and you salt the living crap out of
it and it preserves we block the enzymes
from working so it doesn't metabolize
and by the way this is one of the
reasons why leaving the core in of the
avocado helps as well because it's
secreting those same kind of same things
to keep the flesh from rotting inside
right take that thing out it goes Brown
faster okay so why doesn't that happen
with the carbohydrate well remember fat
protein or aerobic right but
carbohydrate metabolism in order to get
to a Roebuck has to start anaerobically
so we need an anaerobic kick Stern
if you leave carbohydrates out and you
give them an anaerobic kick starter boom
it'll take off if not they will be much
more shelf stable and this is one of the
many many many reasons why all of our
snack foods the vast majority of our
foods that are produced are having the
carbohydrate because they're just much
more shelf stable it's not that this
government conspiracy to get you fat or
give you Alzheimer's or
whatever the hell they they say
carbohydrates do this is the fact that
they are simply much more shelf stable
this means they can produce products and
ship them across the country you can
have a the carbohydrate you like on
every corner and every vending machine
it's pretty tough to get pure protein
that's not dehydrated right so if you
want protein in a snack and a vending
machine it's gonna have to be a jerky or
something that's been processed and
treated like that and also not going to
get too many avocados in vending
machines it's just too tough so why does
all this stuff matter here's one classic
exercise physiology here what I'm
showing you is the maximal rate of ATP
generation in other words all of these
different fuel components how quickly
does each generate ATP think back to the
match think back to the wood and the log
the match Pete phosphate creatine really
fast boy tremendously effective at
making energy quick glycolysis which is
like lysis right splitting up glycogen
glucose carbohydrate come in come back
then that's not as fast but still really
really really fast from there we have to
go into oxidation so now we start having
to use oxygen to create energy and
remember we oxidize fat as a fuel but we
also oxidize carbohydrates so if you
look at that chart right now you're
thinking what the hell's the difference
in glycolysis and carbohydrate they're
both using carbohydrate but that
glycolysis is the anaerobic portion of
it and then when I finished your
anaerobic portion of and I moved the
aerobic or oxidative portion of it they
just abbreviated that as carbohydrate
but both of them are carbohydrate right
and so even aerobic oxidation of
carbohydrate is still a lot faster
probably twice or more faster than an
oxidation of fat and there's a reason
why we'll come back to that later but
I'm not saying that's bad or
carbohydrate oxidation is bad because
although they are slow the inverse is
their storage capacities basically
unlimited I mean look at the storage you
have of matches you can't carry that
many pieces up that much PCR around
because you pack it in the cytoplasm of
the muscle cells you can't carry that
much
the same thing with your ability to go
through anaerobic glycolysis of
carbohydrate in fact the total amount of
carbohydrate you can store in your body
is very very low you primarily store it
and muscle that's the biggest component
a little bit in blood and a lot on your
liver three big places that you saw a
carbohydrate in your body right
but fat is unlimited right if you need
to store more fat you'll just keep
packing packing more in you'll make more
out of both size or adipose does your
fat cells right you'll pack more little
it bends it fat into those adipose cells
it's unlimited you can't do that with
carbohydrate because in order to
continue to do that we either have to
make the liver bigger we have to make
the muscles bigger and you're not gonna
do that you're just gonna take that
extra stuff and convert it away in a fat
stored as fat all right and so now
hopefully we're staying the pros and
cons of both situations and systems
what's the problem right well why are
they why is it so slow like why is the
oxidation of carbohydrates so slow
that's our real issue well we have to go
back and we look at a chart like this so
what this is showing you is how these
different physiological systems interact
assuming you're doing some all-out
exercise again a TV pcr that's gonna be
a match it's gonna give you 10 15 20
seconds of energy the anaerobic
glycolysis portion somewhere in that 20
second domain do a couple of minutes and
the oxidative system takes over so why
is that oxidative carbohydrate system so
slow especially compared to my causes
it's because we now have to breathe in
oxygen transport that oxygen through our
blood get that from the blood into the
capillaries get that from the
capillaries into the muscle cell get
that muscle solvent in amount of Condrey
and get that all shipped in the model
Conner itself when I use carbohydrate
for metabolism and aerobic Lee all I do
is take the carbohydrate that's stored
in my muscle one-step process boom kind
of one-step process now I'm making ATP
so I'll say that one more time
even when I'm using carbohydrate
anaerobically I'm using it directly in
the exercising cell
now the mitochondria is in the cytoplasm
it's basically a one step and it's it's
actually five but one step basically
inside there to make ATP if I want to
use that same carbohydrate molecule but
I want to use it aerobic Li I have to
bring in oxygen transport that oxygen
through the arteries transport that end
of the money into the capillaries get it
from the capillary into the muscle
tissue and then take that into the
muscle tissue take the carbohydrate and
move it into the mitochondria and now I
get it so it's an extra one two three
four five or so big steps and we have a
physical time billion right imagine um
I'm doing some Sprint work and my
hamstrings are dying I got to bring all
that stuff in transport through the body
get it all the way down into my
hamstrings at a sufficient level it's
just too damn slow well the same sort of
thing happens with fat so we don't have
a lot of energy coming from fat from the
exercising muscle we get that from fat
stored around the entire body so now not
only do we have to do that bring in
error move it all transporter thing but
now we have to break down fat that's
stored in the back of my neck put that
in the blood transport that to in the
muscle cell get that in the muscle cell
and get that into mitochondria there's
more detail here we're gonna come back
in a second but that's the big concept
it's just too damn slow because it's got
too many extra steps I got to move it
around so if I'm trying to do about of
exerciser or something a performance
from where I need to produce energy
really quickly I'm gonna have I'm gonna
I'm going to struggle if I'm trying to
use fat as my fuel or even if I'm trying
to use carbohydrate from monoxide in
perspective you've seen that both from a
theoretical perspective here as well as
performance data and a tremendous amount
of studies right so that's very
scientifically clear for the most part
you're gonna struggle if you have to do
that opposite if I'm doing some sort of
training where I need to have huge
amounts total amounts of energy and I'm
only using anaerobic glycolysis well I'm
going to be limited by the total amount
of carbohydrate in phosphocreatine I can
store all bunk
I'll run out of gas right and so we have
to think about what's the actual demand
of the sport the athlete what time is it
how long is the actual event how many
miles am i covering or distance or total
work we need to do
how long want to pace myself and then
I'm going to use this whole oxidative or
anaerobic resort aerobic fat versus
carthoris possible creatine to put me in
the hospital situation that's really
best practices for performance
physiology keep in mind what I'm showing
you here these are not hard exact lines
their predominant energy systems there's
huge carryover huge crossover so even
say 20 seconds of maximal work you're
doing a 20 second all that air and
sprint you're still using some oxidative
systems you're using a little bit of fat
it's not a hard cutoff it's not it's not
a hundred percent ATP PCR and then 100
percent glycolysis or the inverse right
even if you're 25 minutes into a job you
still use maybe a little bit of ATP PCR
or some an aerobic glycolysis so this is
just kind of predominant systems but
there's no absolutes there so to recap
what we clearly just said
phosphocreatine PCR and an mg muscle
glycogen come from the working muscle
itself what's the problem there
limited supply right muscle glycogen
takes several steps several step
oxidation process from muscle or if I'm
getting muscle glycogen from another
place like the liver we call it liver
glycogen ammos ago I couldn't come back
that later fat even from the muscle self
is many cezzah many step oxidation
platform and hats come from the entire
body so it's a problem with that well in
the muscle glycogen context
I need o2 which literally has takes time
got to get that all transported and fat
has an unlimited supply but needs oxygen
as well and to be transported and so
really what we we need to stop doing is
thinking about aerobic anaerobic and
anaerobic as being these things that are
like fighting and competing right there
against each other and thinking more
like these are actually partners one
tremendously supports the other I like
to think of them more
like a gear when one is turning it helps
the other one turn so the signals that
come from we're not gonna get in this in
a video but trust me the signals that
come from anaerobic metabolism signal
the aerobic metabolism to start going
and so what it basically says is hey
we're going quick here we're going hard
we're gonna need some aerobic in a
little bit I don't need you now but get
metabolizing fat get that thing
transported get these things turned on
get them going so when we get there you
can start managing and then while while
you manage that stuff when we're ready
to burst again come back to me I'll get
it quicker you go back and so these are
teammates they're not opponents I don't
hate each other right so then only
they're not fighting each other you know
they didn't know I didn't even get along
while they're actually best buds
they'll probably hop on a bike together
and go for a ride right no problem so
let's take a little bit time now and go
into each one of these systems in more
detail and start talking about what
actually happens this is what the
phospho creatine our pcr system really
looks like so you take one molecule of
phosphocreatine this is the same thing
you give me if you supplement with
creatine you use the creatine kinase
enzyme if you're my class yo and you
never memorize that but if you take some
sort of certification you probably
should a lot of them see a CS and other
stuff love to ask you if you know these
enzymes
okay well creatine kinase will split
phosphocreatine up into creatine a'
inorganic phosphate you'll get some
energy from it then energy you'll then
use to go back take a deep epi
resynthesize them and make yourself that
ATP molecule this is classic
stoichiometry one two one one
phosphocreatine equals 1 ATP PCR no
missing parts there well what causes
fatigue of this system this is one of
the cases where it's actually similar to
muscle glycogen in that fatigue of the
phosphoryl creatine system is a product
of running out of phospho creatine so
again this is why the supplementation
works very very well if we think about
phosphocreatine is going to help power
us through that 1 2 2 3 4 5 10 15
seconds of maximal extra exercise well
that's the stuff of stuff the phosphoryl
creatine has been shown ad nauseam to
help with so it's very good for strength
power development things like that makes
complete sense right you've you Buffy
bump up that system you enhance seem out
of the substrate there you can do it
more often and you can do
longer it's gonna help you train harder
which is gonna have of course a
carryover effect and that's again been
shown clearly larger no question there
in terms of glycolysis remember
glycolysis is lysis means wood of
glycogen or glucose right so we're now
in a carbohydrate metabolism
carbohydrate my clothes well if you can
see on the on the picture on the corner
there these big fancy biochemistry
charts and we get a PhD in human
biochemistry like I did you're gonna
have to go through and not only memorize
these things people have to draw them
out organic chemistry myosin it's all
kinds of fun but I just want to draw
your attention to a couple of things you
don't need to know this in my class I
don't think anyone really needs to know
it but you do need to know on on
certification exam set the net result of
glycolysis is like two or three or four
total ATP again don't need to memorize
that my class don't care but what you
can see on the corner there I've got a
circled in red you go you actually what
happens is you although you make four
ATP in this process it takes you one to
two to invest in the system to actually
get them out so your net is two or three
games okay not a big deal what I'm more
concerned with is this concept so let's
remember carbohydrates and particularly
glucose are a six carbon chain molecules
so the black circles you see on the
screen there each one of those
represents a carbon
and so here's really what do you mean
what glycolysis means you take a glucose
molecule that's six carbons split it up
into two separate three carbon molecules
as a result of that process you get left
of the net couple of ATP
wha-bam it's the exact damn Sam same
damn thing that I just showed you here
where you look at the bottom here you're
still getting those two pyruvic acid as
a net result
oh my roommate pyruvic acid same thing
in our context right now okay don't care
but those pyruvates are three carbon
molecules so taking a six carbon
molecule split it in half because I
split and broke up on right there boom
that had an exergonic reaction meaning
it gave off net energy I use that energy
to make ATP but I still have my three
carbon molecules this is important go
check out the physiology of fat loss
videos if you want to know what the hell
this carbon stuff is all about and why
this matters right physiology of fat 5
and 55 minutes
nonetheless in terms of performance base
that's glycolysis we're done we are out
okay guy call us is anaerobic you notice
this statement car oxygen no co2 to deal
with which is why I didn't car require
oxygen so we have no problem
well the upside of glycolysis is it is
drinking tremendously fast not as fast
as possible creatine
you notice I joked earlier I said well
it's a one step system well I said I can
okay it's not a one step system you can
see all of them numbered vertically
there but it's really pretty dang fast
like literally phosphocreatine is one
step this is an 11 ish but it's 11 very
fast so benefit is speed downside of
course in other words what causes
fatigue of the system well we have a
couple of things that can be causing the
together one you can run in a
carbohydrate if you're out of
carbohydrate you get fatigued here
number two is really the backup system
because what has to happen on the
backend to fully metabolize carbohydrate
it has to go from anaerobic to aerobic
that's right so if I am out of oxygen
and I can't move it to there we've got a
problem and that's when I actually
generate my cellular waste so the upside
of anaerobic metabolism fast downside
huge byproducts waste byproducts that
are problematic so here's what that
looks like if we move over to a separate
screen that gives it makes a little bit
easier for me that big green circle
you're seeing on the your left hand side
there is the mitochondria and so glucose
oxidation or again carbohydrate glucose
I'm not making a big difference to your
starch mikage in all kind of saying this
carbohydrate an oxidation being heroic
well we went to this process you take
that three carbon glucose molecules
split it into two separate three carbon
molecules then as a result we get those
two ATP sorry in red and you get to
things called NADH I don't care that you
know that in my class important for
certifications I don't care that you
know the number the concept is gonna
what you're going to do those nad is
send those in the mitochondria that's
going to go to it's called the electron
transport chain and you remember from
ex-con
that actually will leave you with the
result of a whole bunch of ATP these are
called high energy intermediates
okay I don't care that you know the
amount we're not counting ATP in this
class doesn't matter well if you have
sufficient oxygen sufficient oxygen
available what you will do is take those
pyruvate and ship them into the
mitochondria enter our aerobic part
right you follow along I know you know I
know you are you're smart and then what
we can do with that pyruvate is say ok I
will take that and convert it into an
asset Co Co a or Co Co it now you notice
what happened there I went from a three
carbon molecule to two separate two
carbon molecules meaning I've lost one
carbon each where does that carbon go
you say well the answer is right on your
screen and it's the actually the only
reason why you brought an oxygen to
begin with see because the quick version
is your body doesn't like free-floating
carbon think of it like acid it's a
problem and so you will not it will not
allow you to split off a carbon from a
molecule like fossil or like a pyruvate
it will not let you rip that carbon off
to make it into a Suzuka way unless it
knows you have somewhere to place that
carbon well the very easy way to do that
is bring in oxygen because your body
knows oxygen binds very well with carbon
to make carbon dioxide and so if he says
no no you are staying as pyruvate unless
you can bring in a carrier oh you bring
in some oxygen fine go ahead cleave off
that carbon no issue make yourself a
still Co a because we split a bond again
we got ourselves a little bit more of
nadh or nad we can move that to the
electron transport chain make a whole
bunch more ATP yeah hey we're all happy
now and then we could take that leftover
carbon bond it to a little oxygen and
make it as carbon dioxide kick that back
out of the mitochondria put it back in
the blood transfer it back up to our
lung and go and this is why after doing
things like high intensity intervals
we're going huh and we're breathe
breathe breathe we're trying to rid
ourselves of that carbon dioxide of
waste right now that again that's pretty
synonymous with acid level as well
so the city will build up you'll get a
lower acid higher acid level door
PAH what happens if either I'm
generating carbon or generating are
going through glycolysis too quickly to
match my own two demands or for whatever
other reason I run out of o2 in other
words what happens if I get excess in
the system I can't do this
mitochondria will not accept it right
because eventually what we're going to
try to do is take that tryke silicon
sorry to take that as co co in it ship
it to what's called the TCA cycle you
probably learned it as Krebs cycle okay
and then you go from there and which
we'll get into in a second but this is
gonna be our problem area right so let's
go into krebs cycle real fast so we can
understand what the heck's going on
again you got a chart up there I do not
care at all if you memorize that any of
my classes I want to just highlight and
fill it I want to finish the story for
you really as long I get you so in
effectively Krebs cycle is you're taking
acetyl co a and the net end product is
some ATP some nadh and fadh2 don't care
you know numbers some carbon dioxide and
water it is much more efficient than the
phosphocreatine system and glycolysis
but it's slower ooh
downside okay so actually this is weird
come back later this but let me rephrase
this carbohydrate metabolism Carvajal
oxidation is more efficient per molecule
of oxygen in other words how much don't
you have to bring in then even fat
metabolism the fat metabolism thing just
gives you so many more ATP but it's
actually less efficient per oxygen
molecule so if you look at this here
we've gone from glycolysis three carbon
or six carbon molecule we and the
glycolysis we split that up into two
seven three carbon molecules then we
shift it into the mitochondria when I
had oxygen I took those pyruvates
converted them into a scintilla co way
now we're aerobic right anaerobic
shipping a mitochondria aerobic turn
those into two carbon molecules now
we're asked him Co a each one of those
asset oku a goes to the Krebs cycle and
goes through a whole round of the Krebs
cycle at the end of each round of the
krebs cycle
look on the screen here you can see
bottom over there and other corner each
round
produces one to carbon dioxides which
tells you I took those two carbons each
the other acetyl co a will go in the
Krebs cycle 1 2 so we started off with 6
carbons went to through two separate
threes when in the mitochondria went to
two separate twos each to what to 0 1 to
0 now I have fully metabolized each
carbohydrate glucose or glycogen I also
made some nadh they'll do just like what
we did before they'll go to the electron
transport chain you'll make ATP out of
it no problem right along the way you'll
also make a little bit of ATP here but
it doesn't really matter it's actually
kind of telling in comparison to how
much you get from the NADH all right
boom so Zen ad fadh2 etc their electron
transport chain go
nice little review if you didn't catch
some of that ok not a big deal we're
building to something I promise I'm not
just teaching this for the sake of
teaching it it's gonna come back and
make sense in a second so let's come
back but we're just talking about right
if I take all that stuff and we went
through this animation ready and we
buh-buh-buh-buh-buh shifting the
pyruvate in that and the mitochondria
made a still koi matter NADH good good
good good good but what happened when we
had a problem here what happened when we
made that and we went through that
process too quickly or the ran out of
oxygen you're gonna have to go backwards
in other words electron transport chain
stops it won't work it won't accept
these any DHS anymore that's gonna back
the whole system up things start saying
no we can't we're out I can't do that
because I'm out right you imagine a
shipping logistics
well the warehouse is closed for the
truck starting up in the parking lot on
the parking lot will there you're not go
any more trucks and that's going to be
all backed up and in fact what happens
is the mitochondria won't accept the
pyruvate looks like no no we know we
have nothing to do with that because we
are an oxygen eating material right
mitochondria you know how many oxygen
we're not taking no way sorry
right and so you have to do something
else without mitochondria which is now
entering our waste so this is where
we're gonna start first having our
conversation about - generating too much
waste now if you're a fan of these
videos probably one of the most popular
ones I've ever done
explain this to you already and you
already know the answer so you can go if
I skip something when I have something
too quickly you can watch on these other
videos but video is that use you ask
Andy it's the lactaid series all right
this is what lactate is like the cassada
I'm not gonna differentiate it here they
are different but that's why you
generate lactic acid now lactic acid
does not cause fatigue let me state that
again it does not make you tired it
actually saved you from being tired it's
just extremely highly associated with
fatigue and this is why it gets into a
really high levels or high
concentrations when you become extremely
fatigued but you got extremely fatigued
because your rate of glycolysis outpaced
your rate of being able to bring in
oxygen and turn it into aerobic
glycolysis right or the slow part and so
you make pyruvate into lactate as a way
to stop the whole thing from happening
you then take that lactate and you go
watch that 25-minute physiology of video
on lactate right so I'm not going to get
into there but just trust me the lactate
is helping you a lot but it also
explains when we get it and so what is
that waste really specifically let me
walk you through free hydrogen ions H+
are called acid all right that's what it
is
you've heard of pH right it says some
the potential hydrogen alright so you
have a hydrogen proton H+ that means
acid well as I explained earlier with
the avocado enzymes don't work well in
extremely high amounts of acid
in fact they stopped working an enzyme
is anything that you use to cut to
continue a metabolic reaction alright
chemical reaction so in other words you
can't go through glycolysis you can't go
through anything you can't go through
any of these processes that make energy
because the enzymes that make them work
don't work an acid okay so the enzymes
are the machinery and they eat of the
ATP or phosphocreatine like glycolysis
lipolysis proteolysis any of this stuff
trike so gas the cycle atc all that
machinery stops in the presence of acid
if it gets too high this is what it look
like right oxidation over there no acid
honey do you see that poor humble oh my
gosh like rest in peace I hate a wasted
avocado
all right well if you don't put a salon
that avocado this has to metabolize well
and that's our own fat that's a good
thing right
in other words this chunky moldy avocado
would actually be representative of a
your body actually producing energy if
you dump acid all over at those so if
you were to swallow a whole bunch of
acid pills or something and not die
somehow you would actually not be able
to create energy very well from any
aerobic you-let's fad or carbohydrate
because that acid would stop those
enzymes from working so it's a real
problem so free H+ is acid enzymes don't
work at acid man's iams so the machinery
okay
so what that means is you know machinery
working no new ATP so think back the
beginning video or the two reasons why
we get fatigued we don't create energy
we have too much waste and these things
are highly overlapping right too much
waste stops us from being able to create
too much energy so free hydrogen's means
no electron transport chain function no
electron transport chain no free and ad
no free and ad no new ATP I can't go
through that big energy producing staff
that last one free hydrogen plus free
hydrogens also mean no ATP hydrolysis
that ATP hydrolysis is a fancy way of
saying breaking up ATP so even if I were
to give you a bunch of ATP in this
situation you still couldn't break it up
because the the process of actually
splitting the ATP and ADP and B and P I
and making energy that takes an enzyme
right ATPase and that is it doesn't work
either so even if you can't produce
enough energy that could be a problem
but even if you had enough energy and
you just had too much waste you can't
split the ATP that you have anyways and
so that's really why separate these two
things because you might be thinking why
not just say you run out energy well
then that can't be the case but even if
you had plenty of energy and there are
plenty of situations which we'll go over
later which you have low ATP loads ATP
is not the problem problem is you just
generate too much damn waste and so you
can't even break up the ATP you
currently have because they're too much
waste going on too much acid right
so no ATP hydrolysis no energy no energy
here's no muscle contraction right all
right maybe in a separate video we'll go
over how you actually use energy to make
a muscle contract but you'll have to
Google sliding filament theory instead
so really to summarize that up right
again lactate is thought of as this
thing that causes fatigue but really in
some people's mind George Brooks his
work has shown this pretty clearly that
it's really the message and so some
people call it a hormone actually like
the hormone because it's what tells your
body to go from an aerobic to anaerobic
so it's delivering a message it's not
something you're fighting so there you
were pointing at lactate and causing it
giving it all the blame for your fatigue
problems but it's not really the case it
was really probably the pH right now
we'll have to do a whole separate video
on really the mechanisms of fatigue in
terms of cellular and it gets more
complicated in this but this think of it
as really not lactate per se but pH and
now you have a better understanding of
why awesome huh cool so having said that
we can do things like look at lactate
threshold so this is a very common mark
in exercise physiology and what we would
do is we would say something like look
at the graph at the bottom so what
you're seeing there is increasing and
treadmill running speed right just as an
example so if I slowly look faster and
faster and faster you see how blood
lactate levels don't really change but
then all the sudden we hit a point where
we just slightly increase speed but we
massively increased lactate and that's
what we call lactate threshold so it's
effectively the point in which your body
has a huge nonlinear increase in lactate
production and then what this really
signifies is you've now overwhelmed that
glycolytic system so prior to that we
are creating
pyruvate through glycolysis we had
enough oxygen because we're going at a
slow enough rate where we can get oxygen
in bring the blood get in the muscle
danyetta Yatta Yatta and we can match
the amount of anaerobic glycolysis or
aerobic glycolysis we were going with
with their ability to transfer and place
that in electron transport chain because
we had sufficient oxygen once that got
outpaced you kept generating energy in
fact you started creating the energy
faster and faster and faster
and so all that pyruvate built up build
up build up we started converting a huge
amount of that to lactate we weren't
able to bring in sufficient oxygen and
bone lactate concentrations started
spilling out from the muscle getting
into the blood so when I measured your
blood lactate it takes off all right so
it's a good measure it's something we
can train is something that can be
changed the best way to train it is to
train at your lactate threshold or
slightly below maybe slightly above
maybe a combination and we'll push it a
little bit more to the right because of
these reasons it's often again not is
not because it's causing fatigue but
it's a good indicator of pace so in
other words if your lactate threshold
we'll just use the graph from below
again take a look at it if your lactate
threshold kicks in at 10 miles per hour
and my R km/h and mine kicks in at 11 if
you run a race at 10 and a half
you're gonna bunk really fast cuz you're
gonna have a huge increase in pH right
you'd have to run it like 9.8 and you
can run it at 9.8 for a long time but if
you went to 10.2 you really have an
acceleration in fatigue so you got to
run at a 9.8 but says my max is at 11
I can run mine at 10 point 6 easy and so
even if our top-end speed is the exact
same our maximum speed we could both run
is 20 miles per hour since my lactate
thresholds higher I can learn a higher
percentage of that maximum speed before
I start having a nonlinear or
accelerated rate of fatigue and that's
really the way to think about it and so
it is one of our strong predictors of
endurance performance as your lactate
threshold it's not the only predictor of
it but it is an important consideration
so let's recap this whole video and one
big shot all right we've got our
carbohydrate molecule at the bottom
we've got our mitochondria and imagine
all of this happens in the muscle cell
so remember the carbohydrate you use for
energy is in the muscle cell but not in
the mitochondria the cytoplasm right we
take our carbohydrate we split up in a
part of it I know there should be two
pyruvates there but it's just one I'm
just bigger concepts here right that
process we call glycolysis good got it
great fantastic if I have sufficient
oxygen it comes around what I'll do then
do is take that pyruvate ship it in the
mono Condrey from there I'll take that
convert it in this
Kawai take that acetic away make it in
the krebs cycle runs through the Krebs
cycle some things come out of it called
NADH etc and we use that to make a whole
bunch of ATP in terms of fat that is a
separate process called lipolysis now we
get most of the fat we use for exercise
or for fuel for exercise from outside
the exercising muscle alright so if I
take carbohydrate and I store they call
it glycogen I store it in the blood as
glucose actually to small amount but
mostly I stored in the muscle as
glycogen or in the liver as glycogen so
I start using the must the glucose or
the glycogen for exercise it's coming
from the glycogen stored in the actual
exercising muscle the fat is mostly
coming in the form of triglycerides so
the stored form of fat is a triglyceride
stored form of glucose is Beckenham so I
store fat around my entire body in order
to use that for fuel I have to go
through lipolysis in the actual
adipocyte so I have to break it down in
the fat cell bits of my rib or my foot
or whatever if I want to send that
energy from fat into my hamstring okay
now as you saw from the animation there
your fat is stored in a triglyceride we
call it a triglyceride one two three
triglyceride see those red circles all
these circles are carbon but that red
circle of three there is called glycerol
so a triglyceride Azamat have a three
carbon backbone known as glycerol and
then it has three separate fatty acid
chains they're all big long chains of
carbon that could be eight carbons long
ten carbons twelve twenty-four carbons
etc different video right but they all
have different names palmitic acid
stearic acid etc right they could be
unsaturated saturated fats you don't man
boiling this you've got to take that
highly packed a shaped molecule
triglyceride break it up into its own in
Dominico individual components the
glycerol backbone of three separate
fatty acids but remember that requires
oxygen to begin with if I do that I can
ship that glycerol into the mitochondria
and then because it's a three carbon
molecule it'll actually function pretty
much
like a pyruvate I'm talking big concepts
here you could turn that into a steel
Kawai
goes into trial accounts the cycle goes
electron transport chain same exact
thing you can then shape the Fetty ship
the fatty acids in the mitochondria and
I skipped a step there we'll come back
to it don't worry but you can ship those
big long carbon chains into the
mitochondria you can break them up two
carbons at a time
since it's a two carbon molecule it'll
fall it'll function and process
basically like an acetyl co a molecule
you know go through Krebs cycle
etc etc etc so once you learn that basic
process of how minor Condry makes energy
from carbon it doesn't matter if you're
getting a two carbon molecule from
glucose or getting a two carbon molecule
from fat it's got a function very
similar from there at least mechanics of
it okay
upside of carbohydrate stored right
there in the cell downside come on out
quick up side a fat stored unlimited
amounts basically downside got to be
transported go through a whole bunch of
steps alright gotta take a lot longer
protein is made of amino acids now you
can take an amino acid and split it up
kind of tambul issac and get a couple of
carbons out of it
remember that's oxidate that's aerobic
lee needed them ship those two carbons
in the mitochondria it functions just
like acetyl co a you can also go through
a process where you take a bunch of
these combine them together and make a
pyruvate take those pyruvate send it to
the liver pack those together and
actually make a new carbon molecule
called gluconeogenesis so you're making
new glucose and glycogen from a non
carbohydrate source okay you can do that
but it's not the best thing again
metabolically you're gonna lose a lot of
ATP to make a little bit it's not a good
exchange in terms of energy production
remember everything happened in that
model Condrey is oxidation anything
outside of that is not right in the
cytoplasm
phosphocreatine i did put on this list
but it would be right up there kind of
right next to the carbohydrate right no
component of aerobic exercise that not
gonna go to the mitochondria i'm gonna
ship over immediately again point being
the final end product of all metabolism
whether it's it's fat and you can see
the picture the bacon in there it's got
fat and protein or the sugar cubes or
carbohydrate
yeah I say carbide I don't mean like
sugar bread only carbohydrate from
anything all the good cards do right
regardless of what you do though the end
product has three things and three
things total ATP carbon dioxide and
water you use water for you with things
you use before you make ATP and you take
that carbon dioxide it's waste and you
blow it out
so carbohydrate oxidation let's talk
about fatigue what causes fatigue of
that system well either running out of
muscle glycogen or not having enough
oxygen available to be able to go into
oxidation the waste products then H+
remember you generate that acid carbon
dioxide and lactate that la- remember
the lacked a something that's really bad
for you
it's the H+ and the carbon dioxide that
are the problems in terms of fat
oxidation causes a fatigue of that
system
well none really that's right it's not a
fatigue issue what's the issue a
downside of fat again it's just too slow
right but it's not around so I got
fatigue filling that right it does
generate waste though a lot of carbon
dioxide I guess we have to handle that
as well so that being said I have put
this all together in a five minute video
already that is up you can check out I
think it's actually more like seven or
eight minutes long but I'm not gonna go
over it again here because it would just
be superfluous what you need to
understand though before you go forward
this video or in the physiology of
endurance video it's how you can go from
carbohydrates that you eat so you eat an
actual piece of carbohydrate whatever it
happens to be how that goes in your
stomach how that gets into blood what
you do with that in liver how you store
that in muscle maybe some of that get
stored as fat not a whole lot but some
of it what happens to fat how you break
it down how it's stored how you put it
back in where you store that etc right
so I'm clicking through this really
quickly I'm not explaining it you got to
go back watch that video already done it
right try to save you time all the other
you all of you all of you that already
watched it this would be a waste of time
so you go back and do that but we do
need to acknowledge is this if you eat a
higher fat diet you can bias this
metabolism of it so you if you eat more
fat you'll burn more fat
that's totally true let's also store
more fat right if you need more
carbohydrate you'll also burn more
carbohydrate you'll store more so here's
the net result if you're doing the type
of exercise that you know is going to be
carbohydrate dependent think intervals I
think anaerobic stuff well then eat
carbohydrate before hand it shifts you
are what I get number one that is as you
towards carbide right metabolism it lets
you take advantage of it that's a
fantastic thing okay if you're doing
something no that's the opposite that is
really long duration endurance pace it's
going to be heavily reliant on fat as a
fuel well then maybe you eat some fat
beforehand you bias oxidation towards
fat and that'll help you there now the
opposite could be a problem right so
eating a whole bunch of carbohydrate
prior to a fat burning event may be a
problem we'll talk about this in another
video and likewise biasing towards fat
oxidation when you're trying to do
exercise that is carbohydrate dependent
might slow you down it might hurt your
performance so you got to be really
careful there there's also a tremendous
amount of individual variation here so
you really got to try these things out
before making either blanket statements
or blanket recommendations so in that
result number one the food you eat or
consume immediately priority or exercise
you can bias this equation a little bit
right it can also buy a storage so we
got to take that in consideration but it
doesn't change the net total alright so
here's what I mean
if you eat fat before a workout that
doesn't mean you burn more calories
it just means you shifted more of the
burn towards fat but you also shifted an
increase storage towards fat same thing
the carbohydrate right so it's not gonna
change your total if calories are
acquainted so what I really mean by this
is typically what we recommend is you
keep protein levels fairly consistent
but you might alter the percentage of
energy assuming the total energy intake
is the same the percentage of weights
you get from fat versus carbohydrate you
might alter depending on the individual
physiology or the type of workout you're
doing so fine an athlete who's already
tremendously good at burning
carbohydrates as fat as a fuel and we're
going to do a long-duration workout I
might have them eat a little more
/ or a little more fat they'll have a
little bit less carbohydrate so I'll
keep total calories the same a greater
percentage of the food comes from fat
and so we can start learning to
metabolize fat better or I'll do the
opposite if I have the opposite scenario
right so an athlete who's really good at
fat but just has a hard time getting
going can't bring the intensity early
maybe we'll give them a bunch of
carbohydrate of carbohydrate before see
if we can buy a Centaurs carbohydrate
metabolism and see if we can get some
energy production a little bit faster
all right so that being said you got to
go through this part of the video and
you also need to go for this one where I
talk about how we use these things
individually this is a bit of a recap of
some of the things I just talked about
but I go into more detail this video so
you really got to go through this thing
to understand the pros and cons of each
one of these systems right so to wind
down this is really what we're going to
get to in the physiology of endurance
I'm gonna basically start on this slide
so what I want to show you is how in
fact we do go three to one of these
different systems lay out the physiology
so for example I'll start with the nerve
and we'll talk about okay well what kind
of metabolism doesn't nerve go through
does the nerve use fat does it use
carbohydrate what where are the places
of failure in the nervous system same
thing with with the muscle right we'll
go through different types of us and
we've kind of done that in this video
we'll go through blood long adipose
liver etc etc so in that physiology of
endurance video will take me you just
learn here about the basic mechanics of
energetics and we'll start learning how
or why we get failure in different areas
of the system once we do that we can
then jump to the fun and we're gonna do
that another video and here's what I'll
do is I'll lay out for different types
of performance so maximum power like a 1
rep max for max vertical jump muscular
endurance high intensity intervals and
long duration and trips and what we'll
do is we'll go through each one of those
physiological systems one through six
we'll talk about in under each of these
different performance examples where is
the point of failure or fatigue and what
we can do about it so that's in the
physiology of endurance video so go
check that out as always I appreciate
your support I know this is a heck of
actually was gonna do this as well as
kinesiology of a nurse video in the same
one until I realized oh my god it's give
me like a four and a half hour video so
thanks for sticking around as always you
can tell I put countless hours into all
of these videos this is my life's work
this is what I do for a living this is
how I feed my child everything else so
I'm giving this away for free always
will I appreciate your support it makes
a big difference and it means a lot to
me so because I'm giving this all out I
have a small ask of you of course like
subscribe share these videos etc more
importantly the way that I make this
stuff work is through a patreon account
so I take donations there if if you just
got an hour and a half of free
high-level exercise physiology education
nutrition education and you could afford
5 bucks 10 bucks 20 bucks I would really
appreciate it I take that money that
allows me to do things like check out
how high quality of this video is the HD
stuff the production I can send this to
a production team they put it together I
post it up right so instead of taking
this video probably took me I mean just
to film alone two hours to create the
content to put this together you're not
gonna find this in a textbook alright
this is stuff I've created originally
from my own head and no one's ever put
this together or told me to do this this
way so how long these videos take me
well my whole career is on my tag right
so if you can afford it if you can help
support
I really really appreciate you going to
that patreon it's just patreon.com
forward slash Andy Gump in contributing
whatever you can to the prizes that
allows me to again literally pay my
production team I also take that money
and I can support my students to do
things for me that buying me tying to
make more of these damn videos right I
have a full-time job I have an athlete's
to take care of I have a family my own
health etc so if you want more of these
videos you want to keep sustaining me
making more of this stuff though the
comments are great below the message you
send me are fantastic that that's all
great but really put your money where
your mouth is that's how you show
support I get messages constantly how
can I support what can I do well that's
the answer I contribute I put in 10
bucks put
five bucks you know I've had a couple of
people donate hundred bucks things like
that that's all fantastic if I were to
charge you for these you know I'm
getting a much higher price point for
that I don't want to do that if you
can't afford it fine no problem at all
like subscribe share around and I'll
call that good I'll never come on you
down for that but for those either can
I'm basically giving you a free college
education here hopefully you could part
with a few bucks for that that being
said and with my sales pitch I hate that
I hope you learned something had
some fun and we'll see you back in the
next installation of the physiology of
endurance or whatever hello there video
you want to jump to next thank you